# 大家好 今天我摘點這個艾草來做這個艾油果 (註︰他說的應該是客家話)
Hi everyone! Today I'm gonna pick some mugwort to make some mugwort rice cake.
# 現在春天啦
It's now spring,
# 這個艾草都長起來啦
and the mugwort has just started growing.
# 剛剛露出尖來
You can only see the tips.
# 我就把它摘回去 這樣才夠嫩
I pick them now, to ensure the freshness.
# 如果夏天的話 這個艾草老啦 就不好吃啦
The mugwort will become too old in summer and it won't taste good.
# 這個很嫩的哦 剛剛
It is really young. It has just,
# 剛剛長出來的
it has just started growing.
# 我們把嫩的摘掉就好啦
We pick only the young ones.
# 我們把它摘掉又長出來的
Once we pick it, it grows again.
# 它自己會長出來
It grows all by itself.
# 你看 這裡
Look! Here,
# 這裡好多哇
here's a lot!
# 這個 摘的時候
I mean, when you're picking,
# 一定要看清楚 別摘錯啦
you need to be very careful. Don't pick the wrong one.
# 有一種
There's one,
# 有一種草跟這個很像的哦
there's one which looks very similar to it.
# 別摘錯了就吃了就拉肚子就完啦 (註︰這句文法有點錯亂)
Pick the wrong one, eat it, then get a bad tummy and good luck
# 好香啊 這個艾草
The mugwort smells really good!
# 好有味道
It's so aromatic.
# 比較新鮮
It's quite fresh.
# 好多 好多都還沒長起來
Many, many have not yet grown.
# 這一片就長起來啦
But those here have already grown up.
# 可能這一片的陽光比較充足
Perhaps the sunshine here is better.
# 這可以 也可以直接炒來吃的 這個
It can be, it can be fried and eaten right away, I mean,
# 艾草
the mugwort.
# 你看 夠啦
Look! It's enough.
# 不要摘那麼多
Don't pick too much.
# 留 留一點給老人家摘一下
I shall leave, leave some for the elderly.
# 不要全部摘光啦 就不好啦
Don't pick them all. It's not nice.
# 哇 很香啊
Wa! It smells so good!
# 很濃的那個 那個 這個艾草味
It has a rich, rich, I mean, scent of mugwort.
# 那螞蟻
An ant!
# 咬我一口
It bit me!
# 好 回去啦
Alright! Let's go back!
# (註︰不知在說甚麼，但也說明一下為何沒有翻譯吧)
Conversations in Hakka dialect
# 這個 把這個撞qi的這個 洗一下
Let me wash the, the, here of the "zhong qi" (pestle).
# 我也不知道叫甚麼 管它
I have no ideas how it's called. Who cares.
# 把這個艾草
Now I wash the mugwort,
# 洗乾淨
wash it thoroughly.
# 這個艾草把它放下去
Now I put the mugwort into the mortar,
# 直接搗爛就行啦
smash it, and done.
# 摘這個有點累的哦
This job is a bit tiring, you know.
# 這個手臂 手臂很酸
I can feel the sore, the sore on my arm.
# 有這個東西就很快就把它搗爛啦
It doesn't take too much time, with this stuff.
# 要我 我把它打成稀巴爛的那一種
I, ah, I need to smash it to some kind of a paste,
# 把它打成黏黏的
the sticky one.
# 就可以啦
That would be good.
# 然後我們直接放那個麵粉下去
Then we can put in the flour right away.
# 不是 糯米粉
I mean, sticky rice flour.
# 摘那糯米粉
Yea, sweet rice flour.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 已經把它接的
It has already been ground,
# 稀巴爛啦
into a paste.
# 我把這個撈起來
Let me put it here.
# 把它帶回去 這個是兄弟家的
I'll bring it back. It's my buddy's.
# 等一上來洗一下
I'll have it washed first.
# 我先要加點鹽
I put some salt first.
# 你的手不要搞
Watch your hands! Don't touch!
# 應該夠啦
It should be enough.
# 加點這個 不夠
Put some more, you know. It's not enough.
# 太稀啦
It's too thin.
# 粉放多啦
And now it's too much.
# 我只要這邊的 那邊的不要
Okay, I take only the flour on this side, not that side.
# 你看 這個就很靚 這個
Look! So it's now really beautiful, isn't it?
# 很濕潤 剛剛好
The moisture is good, perfect!
# 我們做成丸子
We'll make it into balls.
# 以前是燒餅一樣的 現在做成小丸子
We used to make it into discs. But this time we make balls.
# 這樣 像個鳥蛋一樣
That's it! Just like a bird egg.
# 你看 我把它做成小丸子
Look! I make it into balls.
# 一個一個
One by one
# 不要讓他們挨在一起 挨在一起它們就粘在一起啦
Put them separately. Otherwise they would stick together.
# 你看 這個圓的
Look! These are round.
# 做了一盤子
So here's a whole plate of them.
# 先 先煎著它來 然後我們再做這個 (註︰我不區分他的煎炒炸了，反正都要倒到一堆油裡去)
I'll fry, fry them first. Then I'll come to the rest.
# 這個鍋已經燒熱了 我加點油下去
The, the wok is already heated. So I'll now put the oil.
# 加多一點
I need more.
# 好 可以啦
Good! It's alright now.
# 把這也放下去
Put them into the wok too.
# 誒
Ay!?
# 可以喲
It's not bad.
# 已經夠燙啦
It's already hot enough.
# 這個很快的哦
It won't take long.
# 像公雞下蛋一樣 一個一個往下
Drop them down one by one, like a cock laying eggs.
# 往下掉
Throw it in.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 會爆炸的
It bursts.
# 你看 它裡面都熟了的 哦
Look! It's also well cooked inside.
# 你看 小黑都跑回來啦
Look! Blacky has also come back.
# 來喲 給點給你吃
C'mon! I give you some.
# 不要吐掉哦
Don't spit it out!
# 吃掉哦
Swallow it!
# 直的吃
She did it.
# 雙胞胎
Twins
# 好啦
Alright!
# 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
The video ends here.
# 留 留給他們 吃一下
I'll leave, leave some for them.
# 不能一個人全吃啦
I shouldn't finish it alone.